Oscar Thomas Olson Papers
Oscar Thomas Olson Papers
1880-1961
Olson, Oscar Thomas, 1887-
9.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American clergyman, Cleveland Methodist minister. Correspondence, incoming and outgoing (1917-1959); manuscript addresses, essays, prayers, sermons (1911-1961); photographs; and printed material, including articles, booklets, newsletters, reports, sermons (1918-1961), and other printed items relating to the Epworth-Euclid Methodist Church of Cleveland (1934-1959).
149418
Biographical History
Oscar Thomas Olson (1887-19??) was an American clergyman and author, active in the Methodist and Methodist Episcopal Church.
Born in Chicago, Illinois, Olson received his A.B. at Albion College of Michigan in 1911, his A.M. in 1913, and his D.D. in 1922. He studied at Union Theological Seminary from 1911-1913, received his Doctor of Letters at Western Maryland College in 1935, and his Doctor of Laws at Mount Union College in 1938.
Olson was ordained minister of the Methodist Episcopal Church in 1912, pastor of the First Church, Royal Oak, Michigan from 1912-1919, Trinity Church, Detroit, 1919-1921, Mt. Vernon Place Church, Baltimore 1921-1932, Wilmette Parish Church 1932-1934, and Epworth-Euclid Church, Cleveland, from 1934-1959.
He was Simpson lecturer at DePauw University, 1929-30, and exchange preacher for World Alliance for Peace, Great Britain, Glasgow in the summer of 1929. He was a member of the Joint Hymnal Commission of Methodist Churches, representing Methodist Episcopal Church, S. and Methodist Protestant Churches. He was a member of the Methodist Episcopal General Conference in 1932, a member of the General Conference Commission on Course of Study, Commission on Supervision and Administrator of Methodist Episcopal Church. He was chairman of the Federal Council of Churches of Christ Committee on Worship, and director of the publicity of Methodist Episcopal General Conference in 1936. In 1937 he was a member of the Uniting Conference of Methodist Churches (chairman of committee on rituals and worship). In 1940 he was a member of the General Conference and Jurisdictional Conference from 1940 to 1944 of the Methodist Church.
Olson was also a committee member on ministerial training of the Methodist Church, a trustee of St. Luke's Hospital, and a member of Sigma Nu, Delta Sigma Rho, and Phi Beta Kappa. He is the author of Some Values for Today (1930) and editor of Book of Worship for Church and Home (1945).
He was married October 16, 1912 to the former Edith Margaret Ketcham, with whom he had three children.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Oscar Thomas Olson Papers consist of correspondence, subject files, writings (manuscripts), and printed matter, including more than thirty years' of the The Epworth-Euclid Outlook, the newsletter of the Epworth-Euclid Methodist Church in Cleveland, Ohio.
Correspondence is divided into incoming, outgoing, and correspondence by subject. (Inclusive Dates: 1917-1959)
Subject files includes daily memos, map, medals, Methodist biographies, photographs, and receipts. (Inclusive Dates: 1880-1961)
The majority of Manuscripts are by Olson, with a few items about him. Articles and addresses, all typed, are first by Olson and then about Olson. Fragments, Notes, and Lists made by Olson are both typed and handwritten. Music includes music manuscripts. Prayers includes prayers both typed and handwritten. Sermons, all typed, are by Olson. (Inclusive Dates: 1911-1961)
Printed matter includes articles, booklets, bulletins, essays, news items, orders of worship, pamphlets, prayers, programs, reports, sermons, and studies. (Inclusive Dates: 1918-1961)
Orders of Worship from the Epworth-Euclid Methodist Church is bound in notebooks by fiscal year. (Inclusive Dates: 1936-1959)
The Epworth-Euclid Outlook is bound in hard covers, by year. (Inclusive Dates: 1934-1959)
Arrangement of the Collection
Incoming correspondence and correspondence by subject are arranged alphabetically; outgoing Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Subject files are arranged alphabetically by topic, then chronologically. Manuscripts are subdivided by type. Printed matter is arranged alphabetically by subject. Orders of worship and The Epworth-Euclid Outlook are bound chronologically.
Related Material
has numerous collections relating to the Methodist church and clergy. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; Olson, Oscar Thomas, 1887-; Epworth-Euclid Methodist Church (Cleveland, Ohio); Clergy -- United States.; Methodist Church -- Clergy.; Methodists -- United States.; Sermons, American.; Speeches (documents); Articles.; Booklets.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Newsletters.; Photographs.; Reports.; Sermons.; Clergy.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical Material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - A-G (Box 1)
    - H-L (Box 1)
    - M-S (Box 1)
    - T-Y (Box 1)
  - Outgoing
    - 1917-1959 (Box 1)
    - To wife from Europe, 1948; 1951,; 1953 (Box 1)
  - By Subject
    - Baltimore (Box 1)
    - Circulars, 1918-1919 (Box 1)
    - Milwaukee defeat, 1952 (Box 1)
    - Pryor, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Questionnaires, 1926 (Box 1)
    - Retirement, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Retirement, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Of others (Box 1)
    - To Mrs. Olson, 1964 (Box 1)
- Subject file
  - Daily Memos, 1922-1961; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Map, 1880 (Box 2)
  - Medals (Box 2)
  - Methodists (Box 2)
  - Biographies (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
  - Receipts, 1908-1960 (Box 2)
- Manuscripts
  - Articles, addresses
    - by Olson
      - 1. Typescripts and carbons, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 2. Unfiled half-size pages, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 3. Filed (Box 3)
    - about Olson (Box 4)
  - Fragments, notes, lists by Olson (Box 4)
  - Music (Box 4)
  - Prayers (Box 4)
  - Sermons
    - 1. Typescripts and carbons, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 2. Unfiled half-size pages, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 3. Filed
      - A-Cha (Box 5)
      - Chr-D (Box 6)
      - E-G (Box 7)
      - H-J (Box 8)
      - K-M (Box 9)
      - N-R (Box 10)
      - S-V (Box 11)
      - W-Y (Box 12)
- Printed matter
  - A-Co (Box 13)
  - Co-Pr (Box 14)
  - Pr-Z (Box 15)
- Orders of Worship, Epworth-Euclid Methodist Church Cleveland, Ohio
  - 1936-1948 (Box 16)
  - 1949-1959 (Box 17)
- The Epworth-Euclid Outlook
  - Bound volumes, 1934-1959; 20 volumes